Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Frank Egbert Bryant papers on English ballads, 1906-1910 (MS Am 2421): Guide.
Frank Egbert Bryant papers on English ballads,,
1906-1910.
Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
MS Am 2421
Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910.
1.3 linear feet (3 boxes)
Papers concerning research on early English ballads by American scholar, Frank Egbert Bryant.
1 collection
This collection is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. See access restrictions below for additional information.
No accession number. Gift of Mrs. Frank Egbert Bryant, Lawrence, Kansas; received: 1926 July 12. Recataloged from 25241.62*
There are no restrictions on physical access to this material. Collection is open for research.
This collection is not housed at the Houghton Library but is shelved offsite at the Harvard Depository. Retrieval requires advance notice. Readers should check with Houghton Public Services staff to determine what material is offsite and retrieval policies and times.
Frank Egbert Bryant received a Litt.B. (1899) and an A.M. (1901) from the University of Michigan. Bryant taught in the Department of English at the University of Kansas from 1902-1909. In 1910 he received a Ph.D. in English Philology from Harvard University, having studied with George Lyman Kittredge. Prior to receiving his Ph.D., Bryant had researched English ballad materials in the British Museum, Cambridge University, and Oxford University, to gather information for the writing of his dissertation, Chapters toward a history of early English popular balladry. He died on October 20, 1910 and his thesis was published posthumously as: A history of English balladry. Boston: R.G. Badger, 1913.
Arranged in two series:
I. Compositions and miscellany
II. Notes on early English ballads
Compositions by Bryant, especially including a typescript version of his 1910 Harvard Ph.D. thesis. Includes student notes taken at Harvard College while attending George Lyman Kittredge's course on English ballads, English 27. Also includes autograph and typescript notes taken, and library call-slips used, while researching early English ballad manuscripts at the University of Cambridge, Oxford University, the British Museum, and other repositories in England.
The University Archives at the University of Kansas also holds some Frank Egbert Bryant personal papers.
- I. Compositions and miscellany
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Chapters toward a history of early English popular balladry: typescript with autograph annotations and revisions, 1910., (1); 1 folders
    His 1910 Harvard Ph.D. thesis in English Philology.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. An English college student's library: typescript with autograph revisions, circa 1910., (2); 1 folders
    Essay describing books left behind by students at Oxford or Cambridge.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Miscellany, 1909 -1910 and undated., (3); 1 folders
    Includes: Phi Beta Kappa card; postcards from H.J. Goulden (Firm); Canterbury and the Cambridge University Library, and other materials.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes on George Lyman Kittredge's English 27: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (4); 1 folders
    Class at Havard College on English ballads.
    Some notes are in shorthand.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. On the limits of descriptive writing apropos of Lessing's Laocoon: autograph manuscript, typescript carbon, circa 1906., (5); 1 folders
    Labeled: "Laocoon appendices FEB copy."
    Partial text chapters and appendices for this paper published in: Contributions to rhetorical thinking. Ann Arbor, Mich.: Ann Arbor Press, 1906.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. The organs of speech: typescript and typescript carbon (both with autograph revisions), undated., (6); 1 folders
    Incomplete copy. Introduction and section with this title only.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. The relation of the standard language to the population of London: typescript and typescript carbon (both with autograph revisions), 1907 Dec., (7); 1 folders
    Paper for Modern Language Association.
- II. Notes on early English ballads
  Notes by Frank Egbert Bryant taken on manuscripts while researching early English ballad manuscripts at the University of Cambridge, Oxford University, the British Museum, and other repositories in England. Notes were left in the order received in the repository. Each grouping reflects package as received. Also included with notes are library call slips from various British repositories.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 1: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (8); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Caxton; The pearl; Mullinger; London; population; health; plague; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 2: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (9); 1 folders
    Marsbach Neuenglinche ... In German.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 3: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (10); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Chappell III; Roxburgh; Dryden's miscellany; Wit and mirth; Pills to purge melancholy; Hume of Godscraft; Suckling ballads; and Henry Bald.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 4: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (11); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Collection of Old Ballads; Watts, The musical miscellany; vocal miscellany 1738; A new miscellany 1730; and The merry musician 1730.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 5: autograph manuscript, typescript carbon, circa 1910., (12); 1 folders
    Includes headings: William of Malmesbury; Edric & Walthop; Fulk Fitz-Warin; Eustace the Monk; Hereward; Wright, Fulk Fitz-Warin; Robin Hood; Randolf Earl of Chester, Clawson & Hale's Percy; Tale of Gawelyn; Judas; Dunbar; Sir William Wallace; Gale; Anchineleck ms.; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 6: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (13); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Ballad in Chaucer; Henry of Hungtington; Comte ballad; John Skelton; Laurence Minot; Lazamon; Waltheof; Trautmann; Percy Society; definition of term ballad; suppased ballads; Stall-ballad title; Furnivall; Schiffer; Freeman; Judas; and Wright.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 7: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (14); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Charmer; Musical miscellany; Chappell; Herd; Garlands; Aldermary; Joseph Ritson; Glenriddell; Scott's Minstrelsy; Pinkerton; Tewkisbury; West's collections; Morison; Wood-Lark; Riddell; Muse in good humour; Foundling hospital for wit; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 8: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (15); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Lenore, Newell.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 9: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (16); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Chappell; Roxburghe; Bagford ballads; Wood ballads; Douce ballads; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 10: autograph manuscript, typescript, circa 1910., (17); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Percy; Tom Thumb; Hearne; Addison; Garlands; Orpheus; Dodsley; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 11: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (18); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Elizabethean plays; Thomason tracts; John Hillon; Gifford; Rowlands; Shirburn; Walton; Pepys; Cotton; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 12: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (19); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Sir Andrew Barton; Deloney; Nashe; Wager; Chuttle; Sidney; Cotton mss; Chambers; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 13: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (20); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Child ballads; Harleian ms; Lazamon's; Robert of Gloucester; Piers Plowman; Herd; Riston; and others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 14: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (21); 1 folders
    Includes headings: Riddles; Harleian ms; Sloane; Wright; Percy; Fairfax; and many others.
  - Bryant, Frank Egbert, 1877-1910. Notes, group 15: autograph manuscript, circa 1910., (22); 2 folders
    Includes headings: Percy; Watson; Burton; Beaumont and Fletcher; Stubbs; Hine; Chaucer; Ramsay; Elstab; and others.